<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The woefull and lamentable wast and spoile done by a suddaine fire in S. Edmonds-bury in Suffolke, on Munday the tenth of Aprill. 1608</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114180</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849408</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849408</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14553</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14553)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1266:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The woefull and lamentable wast and spoile done by a suddaine fire in S. Edmonds-bury in Suffolke, on Munday the tenth of Aprill. 1608</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde] for Henrie Gosson, and are to be solde in Pater-noster rowe, at the signe of the Sunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-B4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bury St. Edmunds --  Fire, 1608 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Woefull and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table waſt and ſpoile done by a ſuddaine Fire in S. Edmondſ-bury in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> on Munday the tenth of Aprill. 1608</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>houses on fire</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Henrie Goſſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde in Pater-<hi>noſterrowe, at the Signe of the Sunne.</hi> 1608</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:3"/>
            <head>THE Woefull and lamentable waſte and ſpoile done by ſuddaine Fire in S. <hi>Edmons-burie</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> on Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the tenth of Aprill. 1608</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no impoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of aflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-kind by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God, but it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to draw vs vnto him, &amp; to teach vs to bend all our intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to celeſtial happines, or to with draw vs from the world, and to forewarn vs not to rely our hopes vppon her ſlippery tearmes: For what ſhal we get by being willing cuſtomers vnto her, but falſe ware ſuitable to the ſhop of ſuch a Marchant? her traffick is but toile, her wealth traſh, and her game
<pb facs="tcp:14553:4"/>miſchiefe: If we conſider where we are, what ſtate we ſtand in, The daungers that hang ouer vs, and our ordinary wantes, and amiſſes: Wee ſhall finde our whole life ſo neceſſarily ioyned with ſorrow, that we ought rather delight (and take pleaſure) in Gods louing chaſtiſements, and admonitions, then any way murmure and grudge at our croſſes, or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations: Conſider (ſaith <hi>Saint Bernarde</hi>) <hi>From whom thou commeſt, and bluſh whether thou goeſt, and feare where thou liueſt, and lament.</hi> Wee are begotten in vncleanenes, nouriſhed in darkenes, and brought foorth with throbbes, and throwes. Our Infancie is but a dreame, our youth but madneſſe, our manhood a combat, our age a ſicknes, our whole life miſery, and our death horror.</p>
            <p>If we haue any thing that doth delight vs, it is in ſo many hazards, that the feare of looſing it, is more then the ioy of enioying it. If we haue any thing that doth annoy vs, the agreeuance therof encreaſeth, with the doubt of as euill, or worſe, that may ſtraight en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue after it: which way can wee caſt our eyes, but that we ſhall finde cauſe of complaint and heauines? Theſe are forcible motiues to perſwade vs to ſuffer our afflictions with patience.</p>
            <p>If wee looke vp towards heauen, from thence we are baniſhed: If we looke towards earth, That is our priſon: On the right hand we haue <hi>Vertue,</hi> whoſe ſteps we haue not folowed: On the left hand we haue <hi>Vice,</hi> whoſe courſe we haue purſued: Before vs wee haue our death, readie to denoure vs: behinde vs, our
<pb facs="tcp:14553:4"/>wicked life, readie to accuſe vs: And on euery ſide, dayly and deadly aduerſaries, readie to entrap vs.</p>
            <p>Oh how much then are worldlings deceiued, that walke in <hi>magnis &amp; mirabilibus ſuperſe?</hi> in greate things and meruailes aboue them ſelues? that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the time of weeping, that make this life their happines, and their pallace of pleaſure: that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eme afflictions to be diſhonorable, that think to goe to heauen, by the wide way, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only leadeth to perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Afflictions are louing and fatherly corrections to winne vs to heauen, The path that goeth thither is narrow, rough, &amp; fully weariſome, &amp; tyring aſcents their way therfore is wrong, their error groſſe, and their ruine is aſſured, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after the ſteps of many that haue patiently trode the waye to heauen by croſſes &amp; tribulations, will not learne to ſettle their footing.</p>
            <p>The contentions of this life, haue nothing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but true miſerie, rough ſtormes, ſolace full of ſadneſſe, and hopes full of hazard: they are like faire weather in winter, nothing durable, like a calme in the Sea, alwayes vncertaine: like the ſteadineſſe of the Moone, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is euer in changing: they reſemble the <hi>Cockatrices</hi> egge, faire without &amp; foule within: <hi>Nabuchodonozors</hi> Image, that had the face and head of gold, but earthen and brittle feete: Or the ſweete Riuer that runneth into the ſalt Sea.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore that croſſes and afflictions or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny externall calamities, are but meanes to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vs of our place, ſtate, &amp; daunger, and but ſeedes of comfort, to ſuch as enioye them, how ſoeuer they
<pb facs="tcp:14553:5"/>ſeeame heere couered and corrupted in earth, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to mans vndergoing, let vs ſolace our ſelues in hepe of a ioyfull concluſion.</p>
            <p>Wee are here but Pilgrimes, we haue no Citty of aboade, but hope for a future place of reſt. If our way ſhould be altogether beſet with pleaſures and delightes, wee ſhould eaſily be hindered in our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards heauen, beeing drawne and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helde, with the view and deſire of thoſe allurements. Therefore God hath layed in the way of through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, ſome tedious and diſtersfull oppoſitions to put vs in minde of our heauenly repoſe, and to teach vs to runne ouer the cares of this life with patience. God hath his ſecret loue to man-kinde, and his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall puniſhements for ſinne, which hee often times doth eaſily inflict vppon vs to drawe vs to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Thoſe creatures which in the firſt parliament of our creation, were appointed to be our comforts, are many times ſent forth with ſundry rods to ſcourge vs, to correct vs, nay to drawe blood of vs for our ſinnes. There is yet a meanes to be made for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement: Sonne and heire apparant to the King of heauen, mediats betweene his Father and vs, to make our peace with him: it may eaſily be effected, if we ſhake off and abandon thoſe viſe enormities, and baſe company of ſinnes, that attainte euery one of vs. If wee doe not, hee will aſſuredly turne his threatnings into blowes, and his louing mercy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeuere Iuſtice: and thoſe conſuming flames,
<pb facs="tcp:14553:5"/>which hee hath of late but ſcattered in diuers partes of this Kingdome: hee will at one time, and in one place, caſt all together, and make of the world one geernall bone-fier and that on a ſodaine, for not making right vſe of his diuers fatherly and gentle admonitions.</p>
            <p>Amongſt which, this affliction of Fire, that befell to the Towne of <hi>S. Edmonſ-burie</hi> in Suffolke, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues with all pittie to be pittied, and to be reckoned (in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of many other) as an impoſition of calamitie laid vppon that place by the hand and power of God for their ſecret ſins and offences. The beginning of which fire, as it was by the remiſſe and ſleepie negligence of a Seruant, So did it proue to be of verie diſmall, and diſaſter conſequence. It was ſuch as none could beholde it without trembling, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any heare it, and not ſhed teares in aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, to ſee the miſeries that were, kindled by it.</p>
            <p>IT hapned on Munday the tenth of Aprill, betwéene eight and nine of the clock in the morning, without the eaſt gate of the ſame Towne, in a place called <hi>Eaſt-gate ſtreet,</hi> in the houſe of one <hi>Randall</hi> a Malt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And notwithſtanding that at firſt it began halfe a mile from the Market place, yet was it carryed thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the violence of the winde, where it did thoſe ſeuerall hurts, as will not be made good in long time, nor without great ſummes of money. In deſcribing which ſad report, you ſhall behold the names of ſome
<pb facs="tcp:14553:6"/>that are fallne into miſerie by the ſame: As alſo the places where the chiefe hurts and ouerthrowes haue bene, with ſeuerall hot encounters, &amp; ſome part of the ſpoiles.</p>
            <p>The verie Market place, that was the beautie and ornament of the whole towne, was the principal and chiefeſt part y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> felt the furie of this fierie aſſault. That place y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before was had in ſuch admiration for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manner of their ſtately buildings, was by this vntimely accident vtterly defaced, &amp; made a rude continent of heapes of ſtones and peeces, of Timber, that but newly fell from thoſe late burnt houſes. The Ware-houſes and Sellars about the Market place, wherein were great ſtore of Fiſh, ſalt, Suger, Spices, and many other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of great value, were by this fire all turned into Aſhes, &amp; now ſerue for nothing but reffuſe.</p>
            <p>This fire broght to the Market place by the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt of winde, hath blowne a great number vpon the Rocks, of ſuch pouertie and Miſerie, that the loſſe that the towne hath receiued by the ſame, is thought not able to be made good againe, vnleſſe the eye of compaſſion extend it ſelfe to the largeſt compaſſe and limits of this Land in her behalfe. The walles, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hedges within the towne, are all laide leuell to the ground, by this furious inuader, who no ſooner entred, but he was inflamed with Pride, and got into the higheſt and chiefeſt places, where hée encountred with the ſtouteſt and talleſt of them, and neuer ceaſed till he brought them as lowe as earth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:6"/>
            <p>The lamentable ſhriekes of women, the cries of poore chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the aſtoniſhment, and wilde lookes of all men at this ſudden and vntimely accident, no man can truely expreſſe: the danger that this terrible tempeſt brought with it, wrought vnſpeakeable feare in the hearts of all that were neere vnto it; but the ſudden and ſtrange cruelty of the ſame, bred the greater terrour and amazement: men ſeuerally imployed, and going about their ordinary occaſions of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, were compelled (ſeeing ſo dreadfull an enemy approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) to flie backe to their houſes, yet before they could enter, death ſtood at the doores ready to receiue them.</p>
            <p>Whole Corne-mowes and Hay-mowes, (the one reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for mans food, the other for ſuſtenance of cattell) were all quite conſumed by this merciles aduerſary. The loſſes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were to great, and innumerable, as none knowes the griefe thereof, for the preſent, but the owners of them.</p>
            <p>But to deſcend from the generall ſpoyle (which was great) to ſome particular loſſes (which were as grieuous.) Let vs behold the lamentation of M. <hi>Pinner</hi> a Grocer, dwelling in S. <hi>Edmonds-bury</hi> aforeſaid, and in the market place, in the pariſh of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> (where the moſt hurt was done) with the complaints and bewailings, which himſelfe, his wife, and children powre out for that miſery which the cruelty of this fire hath excerciſed vpon them: whereby he loſt not onely all that ſubſtance that was his owne, but alſo thoſe wares which he had of other mens; ſo that he is doubly vndone: this fire ſhewed his gliſtering triumphs in deuouring his goods, plate, and money, and in ſwallowing and eating vp a newe built houſe to the ground; that but lately before coſt him foure or flue hundred pounds the erecting.</p>
            <p>He that the day before was eſteemed a man (at the leaſt) worth two or thrée thouſand pounds, was by this vntimely accident vtterly vndone, his goods being quite deſtroyed and conſumed, himſelfe (in his eſtate) was made leſſe worth then nothing. They that before were wont to comfort the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb facs="tcp:14553:7"/>and to feed their neighbours, and other inhabitants with bread, are by this in danger to periſh for want of reliefe, being now ready to beg bread themſelues.</p>
            <p>Many people that loſt their goods, and got from the perill of the fire; eſcaping with their liues, are ſince fallen ſicke with the very feare, and ſuddaine fright of it, and remaine in great danger and doubt of recouery: the fire hauing deſtroyed all meanes that ſhould comfort them in this their diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>The lead of the market-croſſe &amp; the croſſe it ſelfe was vtterly ruinate &amp; conſumed to the ground by the violent blow of this hot encounter. Here might you ſee men, women, &amp; children in great multitudes, come crying out for ſafety, and ready to runne out of their wits: ſeeing that which maintayned their liues ſpoiled before their faices; and yet glad to forſake all that they haue in the world, and to ſhift for their poore liues: many were ſharers in this one ill bargaine, yet in the end all loſers. So furious &amp; fiery was this ſharpe aſſault, that euen that which many men had brought into the ſtreetes out of their houſes, in hope to be ſaued, was loſt &amp; conſumed in the flames. Many of the inhabitants, before this vnhappy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident fell vpon them, were of good abilitie; and with that ſubſtance which God (through their honeſt endeuours) had beſtowed vpon them, they were charitable relieuers of their poore neighbours within the towne; but now euen thoſe to whom they haue formerly giuen bread, are ready to be ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the like extremity of want by them (if they had it) for reliefe: and now their caſes being made all alike by this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous enmy of the world, and vnmercifull deſtroyer of all things, being all depriued of meanes, they are all in like dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſtarue, vnles the hands of Gods people be opened in their comfort.</p>
            <p>But to digreſſe a little, to paſſe from Preambles to the thing indeed, from gentle warnings to the penalty it ſelfe. This ſcourg of ſin; this forementioned miſery is but a verie ſmal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blance in reſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is to come: if we neglect to make
<pb facs="tcp:14553:7"/>right vſe thereof to the behoofe of our ſoules: <hi>Initium autem dolorum haec: <hi>Theſe are but a beginning of griefes.</hi>
               </hi> Theſe ſtrange euents are but prognoſtications of worſe to come, as a ſmoke in reſpect of a more terrible enſuing fire, and like a muſtering of ſouldiers before the ſad battell. Let therefore theſe afflictions and ſome other late croſſes and calamities (the ſéeling whereof is yet freſh in our memories) preuaile with vs, not to ſlumber out our time in careles ſecurity, but to win grace &amp; fauour at Gods hands by amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our liues. For if there be a neglect of this, what will the paines be that theſe beginnings portend? How rigorrous will that ſentence be, that hath ſo fearefull remonſtrances before the iudgement?</p>
            <p>But not to enlarge my ſelfe in this. Let vs looke backe to the miſery and calamity that hath alſo befallen to M. <hi>Cox</hi> a Draper, dwelling both in the ſame towne and pariſh, whoſe houſe the flame of this fire ſwallowed with vnſatiable iawes, and conſumed into aſhes: burning al his goods and houſhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuffe, and leauing nothing to put bread into the mouthes of him, his wife, and children, ſaue onely a little yarne, of ſmall account or value, which he had, and was preſerued by great chance in a warehouſe he had in Rotten-row, a place not farre from the market place aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>All hands laid about them in this firy conflict (as if that enemies had béene marching to beſiege the Towne) to ſaue and truſſe vp what they could, and be gone: but behold how ſwift is miſchéefe, when God driues it before him to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of our ſinnes: all were labouring to beare away ſome of their goods, but before their burthens could be taken vp, they were compelled to forſake them, &amp; to looke about for the ſafegard of their liues, leauing the reſt to the mercy of the fire.</p>
            <p>The deſolate effects that this cruell Element wrought in <hi>Saint Edmonds-bury</hi> aforeſaid, is able to thawe the moſt frozen heart, and to worke a relenting in the moſt obdurate ſpirit that is. Whoſe fury was ſo vehement, that from the
<pb facs="tcp:14553:8"/>Monday it began, till the Wedneſday after, the rage thereof could not be fully extinguiſhed, nor could it bee through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quenched, albeit all the welles and pondes about the towne, were drawne dry to that purpoſe. This heat as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed two hundred dwelling houſes, and vpwardes in the ſame towne, with their houſhold-ſtuffe, and barnes with much Corne vnthreſhed in them, with many thouſand quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of wheat, barley, and rie, threſhed and laide vppe in Chambers, Horſes in the the ſtable, Kine, Swine, and other Cattel: ſo did the rage thereof continue to adde gréefe and ſorrow to a place that of it ſelfe miniſtreth nothing but matter of ſorrow, namely the Priſon of the ſame towne, which in ſhort ſpace (the priſoners for the time being remoued) by the merciles iudgement of fire was condemned to be burned, and quite conſumed into aſhes. Many inhabitants are impoueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by it, &amp; moſt of them vndone for euer: many thouſandes of pounds cannot make good the loſſes &amp; ſpoiles that this towne hath receiued hereby. The miſery of this place is matchles, the loſſes of the people numberles, &amp; their cares, cureles: for what a ſtrange alteration may it be thought to them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were wont to ſuccor &amp; harbor others in diſtreſſe, to be now left ſuccourles, &amp; made deſtitute of harbour themſelues, by the violent blowe of this ſtorme? and euen in a moment of time to be deiect and throwne done from the toppe of riches and well-fare, to the moſt lowe degrées and conditions of pouerty, and ſorrowe? and in ſtead of choice and delicate diet; of faire dwellings, and of ſoft lodging, to haue now no foode at all; no certaine dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but the miery frame of this wild world to walke in: and no better lodging then the bare ground? This Towne ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous before for beautie and for ſtatelines of building, is now vntimely defaced, &amp; ouerthrowne by this ſodaine miſfortune, and deſerues no leſſe to be pitied and relieued, then that affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction did, which the citty of Cannas, &amp; the adioyning places thereof felt ſo grieuouſly, that all the houſes of the ſame being couered and oppreſſed with heaps of burning aſhes, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
<pb facs="tcp:14553:8"/>(in very pity of their eſtates) were contented to releaſe them tenne yeeres tribute, to repaire the ineſtimable damages of one ſuch irruption. I pray God that the inhabitants of this diſtreſſed place may but finde (amongſt vs) parte of the like comforte and feeling compaſſion in this ſo ſad extremity.</p>
            <p>To this cruell wild fire ſtorme that ſo raigned in the houſes, and wrougt ſuch lamentable ſpoils to this poore Towne, may be added another caſualtie and calamitie that did lay hold vpon a carte, comming loaden to the Market with Corne, and increaſed the ſorrow of her owner, by the rage of the flames, which were no ſooner carried to her by the violence of the wind, but ſhe was quite conſumed, and the Corne burned, and two or three of her horſes turned into aſhes, to the great ſorrow of ſuch as ſaw it, and could not helpe it, and the ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcomfort of many, that might haue béene relieued by it.</p>
            <p>The diligent and induſtrious care of the Iuſtices of the peace, that were there at that time aſſembled at the quarter Seſſions, and of many others met there together by thoſe occaſions, deſerues not to paſſe vnremembred: who by their examples ſtirred vp many (as much as in them lay) to vſe their beſt meanes to appeaſe this heate; which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding continued ſo ſtrong in the aſſault, that it conſumed, as is aforeſaid, two hundred and odde dwelling houſes: and for all that was or could be done, it is thought and reported from the mouths of very ſufficient and iudicious perſons, that an hundred thouſand pounds will not make good the loſſes that this towne of S. <hi>Edmonds-bury</hi> hath receiued by this fire, nor recouer it to the former eſtate: which beſides the wracke of houſes that by this calamity of fire were laid leuell with the ground, loſt alſo her ſubſtance and riches of corne, money, gold, plate, wares, &amp;c. of infinite value and meaſure, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſame was formerly ſtored, to the vnrecouerable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of the owners thereof, and of their wiues and children, who by this meanes are left quite deſtitute of means euen to maintaine their wretched bodies with food.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:9"/>
            <p>And now becauſe the conſideration of that which our ſins haue deſerued, is a forcible motiue to digeſt with patience, theſe or any croſſes or miſeries that befall vnto vs: let vs call to minde what God might further haue laide vpon vs, beſides this, or our late afflictions of plague, fires, waters, froſt, &amp;c. and yet not onely not exceeded the bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his iuſtice, but haue ſtill ſhewed himſelfe of infinite mercy: for it is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Axiome,</hi> and an approued verity, ratified by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent of all Diuines: That as God doth reward aboue our deſerts, and in his eternall recompence, farre exceedeth the value of any workes we can doe; ſoon the other ſide doth he chaſtiſe farre vnderneath the rate of our miſdeedes: and (his infinite iuſtice conſidered) his greateſt puniſhment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth not to the excéeding heynouſnes of the leaſt of our ſinnes. And ſeeing the iniuries that we daily offer to ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite a Maieſty, in ſo opprobrious and deſpightfull manner, (being ſo farre inferior, and ſo highly beholding vnto him) are ſo many in number, ſo grieuous in qualitie, and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in experience with all men, though God ſhould double and treble all puniſhments of ſinne, and lay them on ſinners backes for their ſeuerall offences, yet might he iuſtly double them a new, and as often as he thought good, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any iniury to the offendors, yea, and puniſhing far leſſe then their deſerts.</p>
            <p>Let vs not then thinke much, if wee, whoſe offences are moſt grieuous, ſuffer a few ſcourges and afflictions, but rather account them as eaſie meſſengers to call vs homewards, and as motiues to draw vs to amendment: that euery man par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly deſcending into himſelfe, may learne to ſtrike ſaile to his ſinnes, and put his ſoule into the ſafe harbour of Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, leſt remayning ſtill in the ſcope of wicked winds and weather, ſome inexpected gulfe and ſuddaine ſtorme daſh him vpon the rocke of eternall ruine. God grant there enſue not a ſecond affliction worſe then this, by forgetfulnes and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſecurity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14553:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
